So it's 07:06
and we'll call the planning and zoning
meeting
to order.
And
next up on the agenda is roll call and seating of alternates.
I see Anne is there.
Scott,
Steve,
Leanne,
And myself.
Then we got Anne Blanchard is an alternate.
It looks like
she will not need to be seated at this point.
Under
additions or changes to the agenda,
I did have a couple on the,
I'd like to eliminate
old business item 5F,
the bike path,
and item five gs, sale of agricultural products. These will both be covered under new business items and were kind of duplicates.
And then
like to
add new item
six F letter from the Board of Education concerning the community center to new business.
And delete item seven approval of the meeting minutes from September 19.
Does anybody
and I'm.
So I make a motion to make those changes.
Seconded.
Okay,
thank you, Steve. Are there any other additions
or changes to the agenda?
Hearing none,
all in favor of
the changes as proposed,
say aye.
Aye.
Any
opposed?
Hearing none, the motion to change the agenda is approved,
500.
Next item up is public speak.
I see there
you want to speak at this point or you want to speak when we get to the new item?
>> I can give you a preface.
Okay, I want to first thank your planning and zoning commission for
taking on that letter at a
seemingly late
time for this meeting.
But I want to just first say that
nobody wants to see this community center succeed and be built more than I do.
I'm in total support of it, and I want to see it fly. And I want to see it fly without interruption.
And as a result,
Valerie the superintendent of schools
came to me with concerns that she had about the process of the construction.
And I told her to write it, I asked her to write them down,
which she did, and she explained them in a letter that I gave to Jim.
Today,
and I gave it to Eric Anderson.
And we sent to other people in the town,
including
Adrian,
Ed seriously,
and Jeff Maguire.
And
I can't think of anyone else. I would have sent you one Scott,
but I knew you would get it through this.
Venue here through the planning and zoning.
So I want
to have these addressed ahead of time,
so that nothing gets in the way of the construction cycle of the
community center.
So that's what I
why I gave that letter out. I didn't want it to come at an inopportune moment. I figured we might as well put it out in the open, be honest,
and these were the concerns that Valerie had had. So I
put them in the letters that I sent out to you,
and that's why you received the letter.
Hopefully, you'll be able to handle some of the items that are inherent.
It won't be an issue.
>> Okay.
Yeah, and we'll save that discussion for the new business portion of the meeting. But Sure. Certainly, we're all in favor of addressing the items
early on.
Thank you.
>> Any other public speak?
Hearing none,
we'll move into the old business,
and the first item is the update on the gravel pit. And
agent Halsey, if you can give us an update on that.
>> Yes, this is in
progress.
It's going slow, but it is moving forward. I've been in constant contact with
Chris Bell, and I've been on-site numerous times.
At this time the
dirt's moving,
the gentleman that's pushing
it around does have a plan,
copy of the plan.
I
tried to
push it as hard as I can. I realized
the time of year is a factor here.
I
mean they were out there,
gentleman was out there today working.
I believe there's only one guy. And I will continue to try and reach out to the owner
and stay on his back.
But other than that,
>> that's all I got. Are you getting the support?
Does it seem like
Chris Bell is able to get ahold of the owner?
>> Chris is yeah
he just.
He
hasn't been able to make him move any quicker either.
I hope it's a matter of.
Just
a few days.
I'm looking at the dirt out there and trying to fill and trying to figure out what
it's going to take time wise and I don't have a good handle on it.
Okay.
>> My
thought is,
and I'm going on recollection
a little bit at this point,
but we approved the
Most recent extension to expire on I think it was September 17.
With two months
to.
Restore the site, following the expiration of that.
And maybe we should have done that a month earlier if we wanted to get the grass seed planted
in a more timely basis and that sort of thing.
But I would think that
when we get together for our next meeting,
as we're putting together the agenda for that, if it's not done
to what you think is
satisfactory in accordance with the plan,
we should
ask the owner
and Chris Bell to attend and have our lawyer here.
I think, you know, I'm almost concerned
that we didn't head down the path of getting our attorney here tonight,
because you've been getting the runaround
on
who you're trying to deal with, and you've gone out of your way to
get ahold of these guys,
and
you know, have missed the best weather for getting
grass seed planted and that sort of thing.
So at that point, I'd be happy to hear any other commission members'
thoughts on
this particular item.
>> I would say that we need to tell them that you have a week to get the grass seed done.
Completed
in the grass seed on. We probably should have done it last time.
But that's just my opinion, Jed.
It probably could take two hours for that guy to knock that pile down with that loader and the dozer. He hasn't worked in two weeks, Jed,
and he knocked down, you know,
a fifth of that pile in two hours that he worked this morning because he only works a couple hours, but he hasn't
worked in two weeks.
>> I understand that. Unfortunately,
I think we allowed
Genovese
two months.
You know, that our motion.
And so I don't know how we can
expect,
how we can demand anything better
than that as long as he's done, you know, within the two month window, which is by the middle of next month. It would certainly be nice to get the grass seed down, and Jim, you
can
share that with Chris to
share with
the owner. But I think the point to get across to him is
that
we're disappointed
with the lack of progress.
We're disappointed with not being able to get the grass seed down.
And
if we don't have a better story by next meeting, it is going to be time for us to start legal action.
>> Look what they did across the street, Jed. I understand completely. You know, is
>> the example of how,
you know, in this labor shortage, things can get done in a hurry.
>> Every step of the way
that
gravel operation
has not met our expectations.
Yep.
>> We're gonna struggle the whole thing
and it was supposed to be done in three or four months
when they started.
I agree with you Scott.
>> I would definitely recommend documenting
any
correspondence we have with them between now and the next meeting so that way we can show a paper trail
that, you know, Jim's been
pushing this with them and ask for a timeline for completion.
>> Good ideas.
Jim,
can you write up a letter to send to them?
Know, Certainly. Contact them immediately, tell them what's coming, but we're going to start documenting
it because
we're not satisfied with
the progress
that they're making over there?
Certainly.
>> Is the guy you saw moving the dirt around today the same guy that was there when you and I were over there a month ago? Yes, Larry Johnson. Okay, so yeah.
He hasn't worked since that day that he was there yet.
Has not worked. Okay,
>> no,
agree. I have become totally frustrated with
with this particular project, and
it would have been so easy to have it go
and just be done. And
I guess the other
question that I had, and I can't remember, Jim, is
since it is going so slow,
do we have the
hay bales, is an
erosion control measure,
out in place at this point?
>> Yes.
Okay. So I saw the silt fence.
Somebody working on the silt fence very recently.
I
thought it was over the like last Friday, but I could be mistaken about that.
>> Okay, so Jim, so if you could contact
Chris Bell,
discuss this with him,
follow-up
within a week by letter with him, asking him for
his schedule.
And
send,
you know, the letter out to the Commission so we
know, you know, when it's gone and
can
stand by to follow-up
for
the next meeting. Our expectation is that,
and you can back me up on my date if I am incorrect there, by November 17,
four days prior to our meeting,
he is required to be done.
And we were very generous in giving him the two month window in his request to do that.
I have a couple of questions.
Yeah, go ahead, Leanne. Are
you finished?
I
yes.
>> Your timetable?
Just to so basically, Jim, you you used the term pushing dirt around.
And did you say that Chris Bell isn't having any more luck compelling this guy to do more work than he has?
Are you saying Chris has been in direct contact with him and the guy is not seeing any more responses?
>> Correct.
I mean, he's
constantly changed contractors. I think we have the same one that's been in place for a number of months.
Yeah, I mean, Chris has been in contact with Bill, Bill Genovese,
the owner.
And then what happened?
>> Well, I've
tried to
have them basically redistribute
resources, meaning put somebody full time on there. And that hasn't happened as of yet,
but
I'll continue to try. I'll deal correctly with Bill I think.
Give that a shot. Chris has been very cooperative. It's just.
I
>> don't agree with that statement, Jim. He
may have sounded cooperative,
but he's not done anything he said he was going to do.
>> Yeah, I mean the problem is the contractor's not working for Chris.
>> He works for Genevieve.
Yeah. And he only works two hours a day, Chad told me, he's only worked two hours in the last month. Nope, I
>> gotcha. And
I guess the other thing that
Jim, you and I should do is we should, you know, set up a meeting here
with Mark Branch so that we have our ducks in a row. I'm not real
clear on this bonding issue and how that works,
but
that money is supposed to be put there somewhere and if
the owner of the property can't get the restoration plan done, we should tell him that we're going to
do it. And if it runs more than the bond that he set aside,
he's
going to pay for it because he has chosen not to
comply with the plan that he agreed to.
>> So it's the restoration portion that's supposed to have been underway
since last month
and the ex the excavation,
the leveling out or whatever we wanna call it for this know, for tonight,
that's what's only been worked on at at the rate of two hours a day
intermittently,
if that it's not funny.
So that's what you're saying has only been done a couple of hours
and they're supposed to be into the seeding
restoration phase and they haven't even finished the first phase, correct?
>> Yes, and you know, there's,
you see the big mounds over there, there's,
you know, piles of tree stumps and tires
and that kind of thing over there,
and
that just needs to get removed and not buried.
It's been horrible,
just
like the initial
excavation was.
Yes.
>> So Leanne
actually he's worked four hours in the last month
maybe five
maybe five.
>> That's
That doesn't get any more minimal than that. Exactly.
He's
not trying at all.
>> Okay. So we're gonna go with the things that Jed outlined between now and next month as far as the attorney and the bond and
directing them that way?
Yes.
Okay, thank you.
>> Any other comments on the gravel pit?
Okay, I think we covered that.
Next, under old business is an update on Rosewood Acres.
And I didn't have anything
update on that, Jim. I don't know if you did or not.
>> Well, did contact
Grimaldi and
he indicated he would be in touch with me to set up a meeting to come in and discuss.
He had some personal issues going on that has not done so. I'll follow-up with another phone call, but
he's well aware of it. And he's motivated to do this. He just
has some other things going on and
seemingly hasn't been able to come in.
>> Are the other members of the commission aware of a Yukon brief this
Wednesday at 01:30?
Okay,
so I see Anne shaking her head, Steve shaking her head.
So anyhow,
the UConn students are supposed to be helping us out with some economic development
kind of stuff. And, you know, I've been trying to,
you know, push them towards
taking a look at the Rosewood Acres
subdivision
in light of the fact that
Mr. Grimaldi's interested in developing it,
maybe they could help with that. I sent out a,
you know, I emailed
Katherine Lewis,
who's kind of the ringleader of
of this, you know, asking if she knew whether or not the
pitch on Wednesday was going to include anything on Rosewood Acres, and she did not know.
If it did, I was going to invite
Mr. Brumaldi.
I see that
the presentation is going to be
recorded,
and so
if there's anything there
and it's pretty short notice,
Keith Grimaldi will be able to take a look at it on tape,
I would hope that
the
students could work with the town and Mr. Grimaldi to make something
happen over there.
>> Good, can you tell me the particulars of that?
Missed that whole.
>> It's Wednesday at what time and where? At 01:30 in the Community Room. Community Room.
And who is doing the presentation?
>> The UConn students that are working with
Andover as their
project for the year.
Okay, thank you. At the request of Catherine
Lewis,
it's an economic development kind of project.
So, if any of the Commission members or Agent Halsey are available and
can attend that, I'm sure that
they would appreciate the support of having somebody show up. I plan to go,
but I don't know much about what we're going to see.
>> I'm sorry, you said somebody would be taping that? Do you know?
Elaine Buchert is going to
it. Elaine's going tape it, okay.
>> I think it's useful if it's going to be taped.
I saw a letter from Adrian that maybe it went to a number of other people too asking Katherine if the presentation could be moved to the evening and I didn't see any response after that. So, if it is still held in the middle of the day, I think it's going to be quite beneficial for people to be able to view it later.
>> I did see a response on that question, and
the response was that a lot of the students have jobs in the evening,
and so they weren't available then.
And so that's what led I to the didn't cross that letter yet if I got one. Okay.
Okay,
any other questions or comments on Rosewood Acres,
also known as Lindholm Corner?
Okay,
we're going to move on to
5. Charlie,
the update from Planning and Zoning Commission letter to Board of Selectmen regarding speed limit
on Route 6. And Leigh Ann drafted up a very nice letter for me. We sent it to the Board of Selectmen. I briefed the Board of Selectmen at last Tuesday's meeting. They were all favorably
responsive
and agreed to
provide a
letter to the state
reducing the speed limit
in that particular area.
So I thought that was going well. Then there was,
you know, the
subject came up, guess
Adrian mentioned that
I don't know if he saw or the reports of
trucks from Route 6 backing into the Dollar General,
which was
not at all what we were
briefed on.
And so I
think that
there have been some questions raised and that sort of thing. So, I think while
everybody remains in agreement that we should lower the speed limit,
there might be more to it than that. And I don't know where that stands
right now. I know
somebody, whether it's Adrian or Eric, has contacted,
you know, somebody from
the Dollar General and talked to him about that.
And it was reported to me that
the
little design,
the design of the parking lot over there,
and I didn't think it was radiated area, I thought it was just painted crosshatch
on
the pavement,
but it precluded the ability, the way it was designed to allow a truck
that pulled off a Route 6 into the parking lot to make the turn to get around to the loading dock.
I personally think
that if that's true, you know, they just need to go modify
the parking lot so that, you know, to me it's unacceptable
To have.
>> The trucks backing in there from Route 6 and everybody here at the meeting was told that they're going to back in from Link Road. Yep and traffic the traffic consultants
>> did that report. And yes, Eric did contact
Gary,
the developer,
and discussed the matter.
He
said that's
clearly a driver error and
warrants
ticket. I mean, it's
a traffic offense.
And yes,
great.
The traffic doesn't work, mean, they submitted a plan by their engineer,
guaranteeing that this would work.
Our engineer reviewed it.
I think it's a matter of execution of that turn personally,
but nonetheless, I mean,
it's gonna be followed up through enforcement.
>> That whole island that they put in there, Jim, has to be removed.
Yeah. There's no way you could, you couldn't even back the landscape trailer around that corner.
>> Ted, you know, if that's a raised island or is it just marked off on the? It's just a raised island.
Take look. I go by it looked like it was flat,
but
it's raised.
Checking the center of this Route 6 curb cut.
No, the island that comes off of Lake Road.
Rina, can you allow me to share my screen?
>> I thought you were talking about off of Route 6, the entry. I've got a picture here if I can
hopefully pull it up.
>> Yep, let me
see if I can do this.
Alright, I think I have to make you a host.
Okay, try now, Jed.
>> Okay,
so hopefully
you can all see
the
picture from their
site plan for us. And they briefed out the truck would be coming down the road, pull in,
go over here,
and then back up. And you can see the backup path.
Here's the little island that everybody's talking about
that raised up a couple of inches. I see. Okay. You can see it. It almost looks like it was planned to back across that in there.
Now that, you know, I've gone back to relook at that after we had the problem.
And then I interpreted it as based on the brief that they gave us. The truck was coming out and pulls on down the road.
I am hoping they don't come back now and say, oh, no. It was always our intention to have the truck back in right like the picture shows.
And clearly,
that is not
what they briefed to us. Luckily, we do have that recorded.
But this
is the island and,
you know, to expect that the truck is going to back up here and make that sharp turn, it just
isn't going to work.
And
I kind of was,
you know,
I thought they had traffic engineers and engineers that do trucking turn radiuses and all that kind of stuff,
it
must have been able to work somehow, now it comes in that it didn't.
So anyhow, that's
where we're at. The traffic concern is bigger than it was when we were just looking
at
going down,
down the speed limit.
The yes? Last
>> My
recollection is that I don't remember any discussion or that anybody would have agreed with them backing in from anywhere.
I thought that's why they wanted the curb cut
on Route 6
so that trucks could come and go from there.
I don't remember any discussion because I brought it up and I think it was because there
was kind of an unusual public hearing.
Mark Brandt's telling me that it was too late to discuss that. But I had asked at some point
could they not come in from Lake Road and pull in front of the building and go around the other end of the building to the loading dock and was told no,
there wasn't enough room. So I don't think any of us thought
at any point that there was going to be any backing in from anywhere
that I thought they were going to come in from the Route 6 curb cut, pull straight in,
do what they needed to do with the loading dock and have enough room to come back out
Route 6, I guess, because they, you know, they didn't want to talk too much about Lake Road.
>> No, your recollection is correct.
And in fact, you know, I had a question on the permeability of the materials there.
Jim cleared
that up for me today. But
this area over in here
is made of a different material.
This section of the parking lot is specifically designed
to support the weight of the heavy
trucks coming in.
Area over here is all permeable material,
and I don't think we stand the weight of the trucks coming in there.
>> Yeah,
Jed, I think I even recall, and if we check the video recording,
he took his highlighter and drew He did. How they were going to pull in and then back up. Absolutely,
>> absolutely.
There's no doubt in any of our minds
what they briefed us to do. Now sometimes,
and this is where we
need to make sure that
we get what we want in writing
because, you know, they can brief you one thing and have something different in the plans,
and
we're going to be held liable to what's in the plans.
But in this case,
I think the plans show
very clearly how they intended to pull the truck in, bag it up here, and we do have that on video.
Now the last traffic piece I'll share with the Commission
happened today when I was sitting here working on my computer getting ready for the meeting
and I saw a car parked out in
front of my house for several minutes. I said, I wonder what's up with that.
And
I stood up, looked over the bushes, and there was a huge
Dollar General
semi.
It looks like it came down Erdoni Road trying to make a right hand turn onto Lake Road.
And I think he was struggling and had traffic tied up here for a while.
But
I don't know what
the story was on that, but we were clearly briefed
that the delivery trucks were going to come down Route 6
and in here.
And the thing that makes me feel the worst about all these traffic issues
is this was probably the number one comment
to the public, is concerned about traffic.
And
if it ends up
not being good, I guess,
you know, we kind of failed the public with
regards to
that, although, you know, I thought we had done a very good job of trying to make sure that we understood everything there.
But we would certainly be ripe for some criticism
if things don't change from what's currently going on.
So,
but anyhow,
that's,
that was the result of the
lowering of the speed limit discussion. Everybody liked that. I just think there's more to it than that right now and we got to get our hands
around that.
So that's what I know about
our letter to the Board of Selectmen.
It was a good letter, good presentation to the Board of Selectmen. They were all supportive of it, and then
it got worse.
The
next thing on the agenda is
lessons learned from the Dollar General
application.
And so,
a couple of weeks back,
Eric asked me
why we didn't install
the sprinkler system in the Dollar General.
Because it was required by our subdivision regulations.
And I said, well,
that was the reason that
the applicant came in to subdivide the property first and the site plan second
is
so that they, you know, one of the reasons could have been, you know, they just wanted to deal with dividing the property first.
It could have been that they didn't want to, you know, deal with all the subdivision regulations.
I don't know.
But again, having done our due diligence, we had the fire marshal
and the town engineer at the time
take a look at the application,
and they both thought it was satisfactory,
And in fact, it supports
the Connecticut
Safety Code.
But I went back and talked to Mark Grants about that. He pointed me out to this section
in our regulations and I wanted to share that with everybody because it was kind of eye opening to me tonight. I probably should have
color coded it here.
So when we're
looking at compliance with regulations,
you know, it says it's going to conform in all respects with these regulations,
less variance,
blah, blah, blah.
Further,
the application shall conform
to the Andover subdivision regulations.
So even though the applicant in this case came in with a site plan,
we can still
require
and should require compliance
with the Andover subdivision regulations,
which state that a commercial building will have a sprinkler system in it.
You would think that the applicant would have wanted to put a sprinkler system in there for his own protection.
But I figured that was his problem. But, you know, the lesson learned for me
is we're allowed to enforce our
subdivision
regulations,
even though we're only doing a site plan review.
And so I wanted to share that with all you guys.
And I think that gives us a little bit of latitude on
how
to get a better product going forward.
So anyhow,
I'm
not citing you guys at fault,
I'm citing myself at fault.
And I'm learning. I just wanted to share that opportunity
with all you guys.
>> I should have picked up on that and did not.
>> I'm still surprised the property owner didn't do it because I would guess his
>> insurance would be lower with the sprinkler system as well. You know, but I didn't really care. It was his problem, you know, and I thought
I was
clearly,
I had been trained up
by a previous town engineer
that
once the property is subdivided,
subdivision regulations don't apply any longer.
And so I took it, okay, that's
it.
Attorney Brandt who
says he
had his finger in the pie on writing this knew right where to go and
pointed it out to me.
>> There's Steve, you know, apparently Dollar General keeps their stores
under
the threshold
that the
National Fire Protection threshold
that would kick in the fire sprinkler requirement
for that reason. And they're making a financial decision.
I understand what you're saying. I agree. It just
apparently it doesn't save that much money
compared to the cost of this sprinkler
>> from what I understand. So any other comments on
what we learned from the Dollar General?
They had a bunch of smart folks in here every meeting they came,
and
I guess that's why they were paying those folks
that money.
Next item up is Pine Ridge Subdivision and
this is kind of my
inland wetlands
liaison.
We'll
see if
at the last
inland wetlands meeting,
we talking about the, you know, we sent, when they came back and wanted to change the driveway,
we sent it over to wetlands because they were routing the utilities
through there separately
from the crossing and that sort of thing.
And
Agent Wagner over there had taken several pictures
of the crossing
throughout
the summer, and I thought I would share those with you because
it's not easy for us to see from the road what's going on down there.
So this is the earliest picture taken back
in early July.
And
you remember we were in quite a drought at the time, so this shows
the wetlands path
going
through where the driveway was going to be put.
>> We're not seeing a picture. Jed, you need to change the screen.
>> Okay.
That's
a bummer.
Okay.
Let's see. So
that happened to me when I was giving my affordable housing presentation too.
Popped up and I was happy.
I'm
going to save that for next month rather than take the time to manipulate
the system to get it out of planning and zoning on the website and all that kind of stuff. So I'm going stop sharing
while I may add. That was gonna be the good news story for tonight.
We'll save that for next month here. Well,
did it show, Jed?
>> It showed
a massive
structure that they had put in place and it looked really good
as far as diverting any
intermittent
water courses under the driveway.
I
was impressed, everybody on the Inland Wetlands Commission was impressed with the magnitude
of
the driveway construction and how it was going to more than adequately handle
the flow that might be going through there. I thought it was a
good piece of engineering and
in my mind,
they did a good job and the finished product looked
very nice over there. There.
So, moving on, the next item on the agenda is the update of the open space funding
for the Ladano property.
And
we were not able to conclude a successful negotiation
on that purchase.
The
property owner came back
with
a counteroffer. We met the counteroffer
and still got outbid.
And at that point,
you know, because we only had so much money in open space funds
that we were exceeding the threshold of what the state was
allowing to be put in for that, and we couldn't raise our
bid anymore.
So,
thought that would have been a very nice
addition for a lot of different ways, but
>> that one didn't get there. Did we ever find out what the sale price was?
>> I did not. I figured I could wait and read it in the newspaper when it shows up there. And
I think that,
you know,
probably whoever is buying it is going to come before the Commission at some point
wanting to do something with it and we'll be able to get that there.
Any other questions on the Ladano property?
Okay.
Now we're going to move into new business, and the first item up is the annual report.
And so,
I sent
everybody out
based on
Steve's comment at the last meeting.
I put
a little paragraph in here about Walda Grant for the
multi use path long route 316 wasn't approved.
We should continue to
try and build on the momentum from
what we had recently done and make another
run at doing that. The
people that
were
in attendance at the little ribbon cutting Saturday morning,
know I was
impressed with how that brought a lot of pieces of the town together.
And
I'm sure we haven't seen the end of that,
but I thought that was
a great thing for the town.
And I think making safe this ability
to
navigate that small portion of Route 316 would
be important to that project as well and to keep that going. So that's
the only thing I added.
Steve also pointed out to me, I had a little typo up here. I had R instead of area.
Steve, I did not have time this afternoon to run over to see. I know where the picnic table was supposed to go. Whether it's there or not yet, I don't know. But I know the plan is to put a little picnic table
on the other side of
the brook there so that people can have a little picnic that are
moving along the trail.
>> Great.
No,
haven't had time to check it out either. Does anybody know if the picnic table has been put there?
>> No?
Okay,
so we'll take that
as a lookup.
But at this point, I'd like to make a motion for the commission to approve
the report
as modified here.
Second.
>> Thank you, Steve.
And any further
discussion on
the annual report?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
>> Scott?
Aye. Steve?
Aye.
Leigh Ann?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. The motion passes five
zero zero.
I sent everybody out some proposed meeting dates
for the coming year.
And when the meeting fell on a holiday, we shifted to
the following Monday. I was just trying to keep
all the town meetings
we were doing on Mondays because I got other meetings that I do on Tuesdays.
And the one change that I made
due to my personal schedule is, you know, from
mid May, I think it's the fifteenth, moved it out a week to May 22
due to my personal schedule.
Certainly,
you know, don't have to do that, but I think
if it's
convenient to do so,
I prefer to
run the meeting myself.
I think
Anne is
fully capable of doing that, but I just like to maintain the continuity of
doing that if I can, as
long as we've got
time to plan for it that way. If I couldn't get logged in tonight, Ann, you'd have been stuck trying to do it, but I will
not intentionally
try and
put that
on you. So I'll try to keep
that to myself here. So
those
are the proposed dates. I know I didn't get any negative feedback
on any of them.
But anybody
have any comments on the schedule for next year?
I guess at this point in time, you know,
I started wrestling with myself. Should we be
meeting in person yet or not?
And
I thought with
the potential for the fallwinter surge and the fact that it's getting dark out and
winter
months coming,
I would stay
with virtual meetings until
spring, and then we can look at getting back together at that point.
>> Good. What I would do as a matter of course is send a copy of the schedule to the town clerk who would calendar them the meetings.
She would also at that time reserve the community room
if we were to use it.
Yes.
If you'd like, I can schedule the community room commencing
in June. I mean, we don't use it, we don't use it.
>> Just a thought. I would, I would.
Yeah, and we'll talk about it as a commission as we get close, but I would think that if we were going to be able to go to in person meetings,
it may start
May or even as early as April once we get past.
>> Okay, then why don't I do it for April? There's
a change, then we simply
will take it, we'll unreserve the room.
Make it available to others.
>> Okay, sounds good. And so you're going to take care of that, Jim? Yes. Okay, thank you. I did get a
form
in the mail from Carol
asking for
that input.
But if you get that to her, that would be great.
Next item up on the agenda is a discussion of the upcoming plan of conservation and development.
Not due until 2025.
I was reading, you know,
in
my approval of the River East,
I saw legal notice from the Hebron Planning and Zoning Commission.
And their plan
is due in 2024
and they are already holding
public meetings
about various chapters
of their plan of conservation development.
So, you know, it was on our goal to
put out a solicitation for
bids.
Last year we didn't get to it,
but I think now that, you know, we've got a few of the big ticket items finished up,
I did talk to Eric recently about, you know, asking for his help on
putting out the bids for people to
assist us with
putting that plan together.
He asked me to discuss with the Commission
the philosophy
behind the next plan of conservation development. You know, one is, does he, do we want to leave it the way it is and
just update it? Do we want to start from a fresh piece of paper? I told him
I wanted to get good input from the town people. I didn't think we had gotten any input recently
in light of the affordable housing plan and that. I think we needed some input from the citizens
of Andover with respect to housing
and,
you know, what they want the zoning to be.
He asked me if we should, if we want the plan to be more
practical
or more idealistic.
And I didn't know what he was trying to get at there.
And I remember as we were looking
to make the 08/24 referral for the garage over on Center Street,
as we read through
the chapter
on
the town center in the plan of conservation and development,
you could build a case that a parking garage wasn't
the best use for that property.
But the picture that that presented
in that particular chapter was maybe too idealistic
as opposed to practical.
And so I think that's what he was looking at. I don't know that that's got anything to do with putting out the solicitation for bids.
That may have to do with something that we think about and the questions we ask of the different groups
that
we might evaluate
as far as who we choose to
go there. So I shared that thought with you and
think we almost got ourselves into a box where
we couldn't put a parking garage over in the center because it didn't comply with the lofty
idealistic thought that it had there. But Eric did a good job of walking us through all the places where the plant did support putting a garage over there,
so that's that.
Any questions on plant and conservation and development?
But getting that rolling is my next big project
where I'm at
with everybody.
At the last Board of Selectment meeting,
next item is opting out of the accessory dwelling unit requirements.
I briefed the Board of Selectment on that.
They ratified our decision.
You know, it required a twothree majority.
We only had four members present,
and all four of them voted in favor to ratify
the thing. So, that gave us 80%,
and that's a done deal. We are now opted out.
Next item on new
business is the sale of agricultural
products grown on premises.
And Jim, did you want to talk about that for a minute? Sure. I had a woman
>> approached me about selling,
well, about a potential
business opportunity at the end of Hutchinson Road. And it was just she's
just looking at it trying to set up sort of a business plan.
And it just came to light how
restrictive
our
regulations
are for just some of these small
tiny venues. I mean, literal read of the regulations would
tell me that if you have a cooler at the end of the driveway with a sign that says eggs,
then you need a site plan. When in reality,
I certainly haven't
called anybody on that.
But then these things grow. Her particular property happens to be in a business zone, which changes
it a little bit. But right now you need a site plan at a cost of about $310
And that would be a very rudimentary hand drawn
sketch, the $2.50 for the site plan application, 60 for a state fee. And I'm
not looking for the commission to interpret
it. I just
bring it to their attention.
Swamin,
I don't know at what scale,
I was trying to get a handle on what scale she would need
to come to the commission.
Quite frankly,
the rate is if she does anything, anything where somebody comes to the house
and I'm just,
I was just, I don't know whether this
individual is on
the zoom tonight or not.
They
certainly knew about the meeting.
>> Well, hey,
I've
got a note here,
Marina, that's up on top of my screen that
looks like the school superintendent
has entered the waiting room, wants to be admitted.
Do you see that?
>> Let
me see. I might have to remake me the host. Oh, yes, reclaimed host. Okay. Let me add Valen.
>> Okay. Yep. I don't know how long she was waiting there, but
all sudden I recognize you made me the host and I was probably the only guy seeing that
thing.
Good evening.
We
got you here just in time. We're just finishing up
the sale of agricultural products and then we'll be on to the new business, your concerns,
Valerie.
Anything else on that, Jim?
>> No, was just looking for any feedback if there was any. We wanted to bring the matter to the Commission's
attention.
I don't know if there's any ability to loosen up on that, revisit that regulation or not.
>> Certainly
not in the near term. And I would think the Commission might like to see a rudimentary site plan that shows,
you know,
she what kind of stand she'd want to put, what kind of facility she has to allow cars to come in,
you know, what she thinks for parking. And again, if it's on Hutchinson Road, that's
I'm surprised
that there would be much business over that way. No, But it's not an idea. It's
>> a lot of drive by traffic. It's the end of a cul de sac. Okay, yep. Okay,
that's fine. We should have a last minute inquiry and I threw it on there.
I didn't really
flesh it out before
it went on the agenda. Yeah. And just
>> so the Commission knows, so I think this person reached out to,
I think it was Elaine Bouchardt,
head of the Economic Development
Commission, who,
you know, forwarded her idea to me.
I wrote back a bunch of stuff about farming on lots that are bigger than three acres and that, you know, how we would approach this.
I didn't know where she lived. Turns out she lives in a lot that's in the business district.
Agriculture
is one of the allowed things there by site plan.
So, I think it's very easy to do. I
regret that it'll cost her $240
to come talk to us, but
I do think
we owe it to ourselves.
Maybe Jim can do that, but we need to know what it is that she really plans to do. And sometimes until you come talk to a group of people, you don't have
it as clear in your head as you think it might be.
>> I think she's going to structure her business plan accordingly.
>> Okay. So, more to follow on that. Nothing
for us tonight.
Marina, if you can allow me to share my screen again, I want to pull up the
letter that we got
from Jerry here so that we can have that.
Should be good now.
>> Okay,
and so probably,
I don't know that everybody had a chance to
read through
this letter that
that I think came in to Jim this afternoon,
sometime today.
But, you know, separately,
you know, a discussion that
I had
with Ann,
we were talking about parking a little bit.
And so,
I know that
Jerry was wanting to get the concerns out
and might not have known exactly how to go about that, but I certainly applaud the
being proactive,
taking the initiative, and getting them out on the table early so that we can
deal with them. I thought
reading through the letter, I haven't studied it much, but I did read through it today,
all those things were
certainly great questions.
My
thought
is that,
you know, I think,
Jerry, were you and Anne
at the public information meeting we had back in
April or whatever it was?
Yes, I was there.
>> Yeah, thought
you were.
Certainly,
we as a commission
have not seen anything coming our way yet,
and we will,
you know, we're going to have to make a
determination whether or not
the plan
is supported by the plan of conservation and development is consistent with
the town plan and that sort of thing.
Having said that, if
you went to that meeting,
you're aware that there is a
community center
building
commission who has been meeting and working hard on that for a long time.
And I was thinking, you know, and I think the lead in to this said you had sent this to Ed Sariski.
He is the lead on that. That's probably
an even better place.
Certainly coming through the Commission, you will get a chance to have your
questions answered
before
the plan is approved.
I don't know where we stand on developing the site plan
right now.
But my thought would be the
best way to approach it, it would be through the Community
center building
committee and
interact with them to try to get
these things
considered in
finalizing that plan
before it ever comes here. And then if it doesn't
get considered,
you know, we have the opportunity to
act on that here as well.
But
having
said that, I know you gave a couple of comments
early on in public speak.
Would
you or the school superintendent,
you'd like to
make make any comments on on the letters at this point?
>> Valerie
came
up with these concerns that she had.
And I told her, I said, I think that we should
make them public and
let people
look at them and
come up with solutions if there was a problem.
I didn't want anything to get in the way of this
community center.
People in Andover been waiting for it for a long time.
Many people are looking forward to it as I am too.
But I just wanted to be upfront,
if she's if Valerie has concerns.
I wanted to share those and have them shared with the people who are involved.
So,
if Valerie would like to speak to the specifics of some of them just to give you an idea,
maybe some background and where she
where her thinking is coming from.
I would invite her to do that if it's okay with you.
Oh, that'd be great.
>> Thank you. Thanks, Jed. Thanks, everybody.
Yep. Their concerns
and, of course, like Jerry said, I know that this is a great project,
and it absolutely does need to be seen through to fruition.
It's just
with the school,
I know that we have so many other guidelines that normal building projects wouldn't necessarily
have to consider going into such a thing.
We have so many mandates
that are associated with the fact that we have
a preschool program
and that we are funded through school readiness and through smart start,
and that goes through the office of early childhood education.
So
there are probably a fair number of concerns that wouldn't normally come up.
It just does for us because of our association
with the state and our funding with OEC.
So when Jerry and I started to talk about these things,
I kind of pulled a few of the things directly from the OEC handbook.
There may be others, but I would love to be able to collaborate with the committee, the building committee. I know they're gonna wind up putting an RFP together,
and these may be some of the areas if we don't have somebody at the town level
that has expertise in this
type of building that we we may, you know, need a little heads up on. I do know that we'll need timelines
on things so that we can work together
to make sure that we don't violate any of the things that we need for compliance
in fear losing funding there. So I think it could be done. It's just gonna probably take a little bit of collaboration between
now and the end of the process to make sure that,
you know, we check the boxes and say, yep, we got this.
And so I look forward to that. I would, you know, just say along the way, if anybody does need any assistance with some of these guidelines,
some of the things that we have concerns about, please let me know. I'd be glad to provide that.
>> Okay,
thank you. And
again,
I think you've probably been made aware, well,
know you have heard
at the public meetings we had, there has been some friction in the past
between the seniors and the school.
And
I'm hoping that we are making headway
on that and certainly
don't want to derail any of those efforts that seem to be having us head in the right direction.
But I do think that the proactive approach
is
the right way to go. And
so thank you, thank you for the letter.
Scott, are you,
you're on the, that
committee, are you not? I am, yes.
I
looked online just trying to get
a feel for
it appeared to me that there has not been a meeting of that committee since probably March or April. Is that correct? Correct. Working
on the RFP.
>> Yeah. So
this
is a great time for the letter to come in.
Jerry, I would encourage you to get
in touch with Ed, who's the chair of that committee, and
see if,
you know, he might want to have a meeting to get together to discuss the letter or that sort of thing.
Because really it would be nice to have that hashed out before it gets presented to us as a final plan and would save
money
too. So, it'd be easier and cheaper.
Ted, could you scroll down to three, please? Yep.
>> I had a question on three. Is three relative
to the overall
as built plan or relative to the drinking water
conditions during construction?
>> Steve, I think it would be both.
Because I know anytime, like, we report a project that's within proximity,
they will ask for certain OEC will ask for certain testing to be done along the way.
And then when a project's completed,
they will request, like, a final.
For example, whenever we move
a room,
cool uses.
Cool has restrictions and requirements as well. We moved the cool program from the gym
to a room upstairs,
and we had to by mandate repeat radon testing and repeat lead testing
because they just require felt really bad because cool had to pay for it twice. But
so
I think it's both honestly to answer your question, it would be both, we'd be asked to produce documentation that it's safe during and after.
>> I would, I would think the end after is in the final product should be
controlled by the building codes etc it's just the during construction where could get tricky, and that I think number two addresses that as well.
>> Steve, I think Eastern Highlands Health District actually does the after part. They
check to make sure everything's good
because we do have to have an annual report from them. Yeah. There's a lot of stuff that they require.
That's why I got a little nervous because I was like, this is so doable and so but we just have to make sure that we we could do it along the way because they give you timelines to get this stuff to them before they give us our money. We're
>> talking about
conditions that would be added to the bid documents
that would provide would
address your concerns here, it would seem.
I mean, that's a function of the engineer preparing the documents
for the most part.
>> I think so. And I think they're all pretty reasonable questions.
I think, you know,
in hindsight, maybe it would have been great to have somebody from the school board on the committee working because
they are the
big stakeholder
in very close proximity. But
I certainly appreciate,
you know, again,
the proactive nature of getting the items addressed and
we as a commission can be looking to make sure that
those items are addressed when the site plan eventually does
come to us.
>> See the RFP is posted on the town website.
So I'm amazed how detailed that is. It's a lot of stuff involved,
and maybe some of these things are in there. I can't tell at first glance, but
I think it's really important to have these things listed out ahead of time.
>> I do, too, and I think that a lot of the questions are probably not questions that we would
have raised
as the Commission. It's certainly not in
our regulations
to
take all those. Although we can ask those questions
in our hearing
earlier is better for them to be working on that.
>> Jen, I want say thank you and the Commission
and Jim
for
accepting this onto your agenda this evening.
I appreciate your commission members for the work you're doing,
and you for the work you do, and Jim,
especially your help this afternoon when you looked at this and got it out so quickly.
So I just wanna say thank you to all of you. You're welcome.
>> Any other questions for us while you're
here? You or Valerie?
>> No, thanks, Jed. And again,
I echo what Jerry said. But if there are any documents or things that you guys need from us where we could help you providing,
you know, the school side and the State Department stuff, please let me know. I'll be glad to get together whatever you need. Okay, so thank you very much.
>> And with that,
that concludes the new business.
Next up is correspondence
item eight.
Jim, we have anything on that? Nothing else. That letter was
it.
>> Okay. The letter from the Board of Ed.
Item nine, administrative reports.
>> Ongoing
enforcement.
We have
Center Street is
pretty much cleaned up.
I do expect an application
from them. I believe
that
the owner will be looking to put an accessory apartment
on that site.
There will be an opportunity to further clean it up, but that will require a site plan approval, I believe.
Route 6, the Barnett property.
Is the size of that live gym?
It's less than.
It's.
>> I don't know offhand. I think it's little over I think it's the biggest lot down there, isn't it?
Little over half an acre maybe, Jud.
>> Yep. So
it's that small,
and again, I have no idea.
It looks, I know those lots over there are small.
Right now,
our
regulations require
60,000 square feet, about an acre and a half.
So he might need to go and get a variance on that before he comes to us.
Hang on. I'm gonna look it up right now.
>> Good. I I understood Mark Francis.
Response
on my inquiry to say that that
wouldn't be the case, but I will go back and
take a look at that.
>> Now, if we hadn't opted out of,
you know, the public act regulations
that would have given everybody the opportunity
to build an accessory apartment as of right, we just opted out of them.
And we opted out of all of them.
And that doesn't mean we can't change,
but right now
our regulation
says 60,000
square feet and
we had
a guy,
I think it was out on Wheeling Road that we,
with a one acre lot, we didn't allow him to build an accessory dwelling unit.
It's point eight The information
>> that I have from Mark Brantz
on that. Okay, well we'll
>> take a look at it.
Most of them getting a variance,
know what the regulation says.
0.86,
>> good. Okay, yep.
We'll have to come through that issue.
There's already a house on it.
>> It's The a house there is fine. It's yeah. The
There isn't any more.
Yeah.
But he can rebuild whatever he had, right?
Exactly right?
>> And he he does have variance on some
of the setbacks.
Okay,
yeah.
>> But that's it. The side yard and the front yard.
Route 6, Steve Barnett property.
I
meet with him on a biweekly basis to just monitor progress.
He
does seem to be throwing things out and hiding things better.
The
Wheeling
Road property,
generally bought the older greenhouse right on the road that's been vacant for years and years,
There hasn't been any progress on that.
It was very
responsive when I initially pointed out to him the need for a dumpster and take care of the site. And I did send a
citation
to him, and that time period that he was allowed to clean it up has expired. So I'm going to have to initiate
the next step, and I don't know what that is offhand.
I'm going to have to work with
the town attorney and
figure out where to go with that. What property are you talking about?
Yeah, Long
Hill. I said Wheeling again. Long Hill. Long Hill.
The the greenhouse on the corner, right?
Green. I thought you're okay.
>> I said I think I said Wheeling again. I'm sorry.
I don't know why.
And so he won't get a dumpster?
>> Well.
I haven't responded
initially.
Did did have a dumpster on-site
filled it and it was gone.
And now I mean my biggest concern is that the garage doors are open.
I mean, not only could somebody get in there, but I
it's just visually visually unattractive
and there's
all over the net trash, but there's wood wood products and you know it would be one thing if there was progress going on, but there's not.
I haven't seen any haven't seen anybody there.
I haven't seen any sign of activity there.
The next Was
>> it little bit bigger of a job than just changing the roof?
>> Oh, yeah. Yeah. But I I thought, you know, I spent a fair amount of time with the gentleman that bought it, bought it with his son, and he seemed to
have a good handle on the scope of work. I mean, it wasn't his first first
acquisition.
I'm also trying to work with the owner of the property adjacent to the library to fix the fence.
It's in disrepair.
And that's slow going.
I haven't seen any progress on that.
Other than that,
there's been a fair amount of activity in town.
A couple of houses are approaching completion.
One on Gilead.
The house on Webster Lane.
Number of large additions.
That's about it.
Any questions?
>> And I won't ask Jim the question because
I don't think he's done that yet and it was me late getting to him, but
I have now sent into Jim the
revised
regulations
with our chapters fifteen and seventeen,
and those should be posted
anytime now, now that we've got an admin assistant
over at the town hall to work on those things.
And I understand we've got an applicant for a board clerk.
>> We do.
So, we'll
be interviewing that individual. I don't know who it is offhand.
Okay.
>> Anything else, Jim? No. Okay.
And I don't have anything else on the Inland Wetlands Water Corners Commission. I'll figure out how better to
get those photos so that you can take a look at them for the next meeting.
I was gonna
copy and paste them into my little handout and
they said, I'll just be slick and put the link there.
Can you send that to us?
>> Yeah, I can.
Yes,
I'll send everybody
out the link. It's on,
that's easy to do. Okay.
Number 10,
public speak.
We got nobody from the public left.
At this point, any Commission members have any questions or comments on anything at all that
you want to share with the Commission?
>> I want to just say that the only reason I didn't say anything about the
community center was I believe that that
letter should be brought up with the
appropriate board
so we can address those things
first.
>> I agree, and
I got the impression he didn't really know
what the process was
or how to approach it. And
he was coming over to Jim to
get a little help there, and I think we were able to do that.
Would have And been nice to have that information
even earlier in the process, but
Right. We think it got
>> to us. Somebody
brought that up about six or eight months ago, I think, some of that information,
Talking to the school about what
was going on over there, I don't know. Okay, yep. I
>> know. Well, I've tried looking online for the committee meetings and such, and there was nothing there for like last four So months or I wasn't sure who was doing what at this time,
but we did send that letter to
Adrian,
Ed Serizli,
and Eric,
and also to Jeff Maguire,
so that we tried to cover all the possible areas that would be involved with it.
Anne, can you send it to me also, please?
>> Okay. I think you got it in the email today from
Jim. I didn't
see it.
>> I know I got it. Yeah. I got it as well. Everybody.
>> Believe I Send it to you when we get done, Scott. Alright.
Any other Commission member comments?
Okay.
Hearing none,
next item is next regular scheduled meeting,
November 21. I checked the date this time. We got it right? All right.
And
>> if there's nothing else,
I'll make a motion to adjourn.
Second.
Anybody
opposed?
Hearing none, the motion passes five-zero-zero.
Thank you all for your participation and attendance tonight, and
I appreciate all the support. Thank you. Good night.
Thank you.